well this is exciting this is a new
venue and it is my sincere hope and aim
that every two weeks we can gather here
and have meaningful conversations about
important matters
of our time those important matters of
course in a very abstract way are
defined by what's important to us as
individuals but also what's important to
us as a collective and it's in
navigating the relationship between the
individual and collective in a
meaningful way while making sense of
what's going on that seems to be the
ticket towards at least a decent stab at
continuity into the future for the human
race now it's quite a broad thing to say
just to chuck that one in at the end
there but that is how it sort of seems
to me
extinction rebellions happening at the
moment in the UK it's going on fairly
big and there's been stuff happening
here in Melbourne and that seems like a
necessary piece of the awareness puzzle
but as far as I'm concerned
climate activism and climate change is a
type of behavior or attitude towards a
particular crisis we're facing and there
are many crises we're facing and it
seems to me like the sense-making crisis
and the meaning crisis are really core
to being able to make effective
decisions about anything else if we
can't really make sense of what's
happening in the world becomes difficult
to know what actions we should take in
it you know we're complex processes
ourselves and we're embedded in many
many complex processes in nature and
culture so it is my hope and aim for
that a very simple and beautiful way to
begin presencing
and developing in relationship to that
territory can be at least heartily begun
by gathering together in community to
listen and speak with authenticity
regarding what comes up and well where
we go from there is is something
entirely up for discussion so all right
then
now this evening it's the first event in
this venue here and joining me is my
good friend cam Duffy now cam I'm not
going to introduce you no I
will introduce cam that was an error cam
works as a dual diagnosis counselor of
individuals and their families you'll
hear me later in the conversation
referred to that as a vocation and does
seem to me at least that there's a deep
element of how cam shows up in the world
which signifies to me that a calling of
his is precisely to enable people to
realize their potential in a therapeutic
setting is not not not limiting his
showing up to that to that descriptor
but that's something I happen to respect
a lot and it's something I value highly
for he has an interest in human
development the art of shadow
integration therapeutic growth he also
has a passion for the philosophy and
science of holistic health functional
optimization and peak experiences that
enable realization of our creative
potential I found a very special very
special capacity to engage in a
constructive and beautiful dialogue
with you and I'm really interested to
share that okay so I guess maybe you can
all hear me okay anyway but I'm just
going to start talking into that just so
perhaps for the recording maybe it
sounds roughly the same so I suppose
before we really get going does anybody
have any questions does anybody have
anything to say is there anything
anything that's mysterious that's on the
tip of your tongue that you feel like
voicing and if not it's totally okay the
silence is good all right I think
perhaps what you might do is just take
30 seconds in silence together and then
cam and I will begin a dialogue and
we'll see where we get to so okay just
take a few a few seconds to drop into
yourself perhaps shut your eyes
I just feel feel the Noize feel what it
is to be on your chair
feel what it is to have your mind do
many different things all at once feel
what it is to be a flux of many
different feelings and then at the same
time I sought a voice that's looking to
bring some sort of coherence to all of
that and just feel the silence hmm all
right well thank you all for being here
and see what fun we can have in this
dialogue now joining me is camp and this
is the title of this event is this
connection in the age of connection and
they seem to me to be two really
fundamental concepts and importantly
they are concepts that can be felt
there's a real sense in which this
connection connection continuity
discontinuity who you are who you will
become all of these things are related
somehow they're related in this flow of
life and the
relationship we don't talk about much
but it is know where we know it's one
that we're on the pulse of it sort of
seeking seeking connection about
constantly finding ourselves
disconnected
and then we find ourselves connected
again so perhaps just as a opening for
this discussion cam what interested you
to be here this evening
okay says you've just mentioned this
idea of connection and disconnection is
such a primary part of who we are is
that journey as we go on our journey
through our life and we make meaning
through what we experience as a feeling
of connection often mmm you know and we
strive so much in our lives to overcome
challenges towards achieving a sense of
connection and whatever way we attempt
to do so
so it's inherently meaningful for every
one of us I think and it's a very
personal thing the idea of connection
and things that may be attributed to
towards the tendency towards
disconnection so we're all humans and
this is a very human experience
connection and relative disconnection as
we go through the various challenges or
hardships that we might be challenged
with in our lives right there's two
things that come up for me a little bit
in thinking about connection and
disconnection there are they're also
very broad things one is fear and the
other is love it's difficult to imagine
feeling love in a mode of disconnection
fear in the mode of connection will
perhaps that's a little bit perhaps that
is something we can get out
we feel losing connection hmm you know
was interesting we met together for the
last voice Club event to have an inquiry
into what does it mean to be fearless
and I think a lot of meaningful things
came up that evening connection and
disconnection was something that came up
there was a sense in which the
experience of fear was one of being
somehow disconnected from yourself and
the title for that event was actually
something that cam came up with and I
was excited to do it because it was
something camp came up with so I wonder
cam what comes up with you with respect
to fear here and how it relates to what
it means to be connected to yourself or
or disconnected from yourself the first
perspective that comes to mind for me is
one of human development and the
tendency of our nervous systems to
advice towards achieving a sense of
certainty so the neural pathways
associated with survival those which
reinforced or prioritized in our systems
but with that comes sometimes it can get
locked in for instance with trauma and
that can lead to disconnection from the
body sometimes in heightened states of
trauma you can just totally dissociate
and there is this tendency to disconnect
when the body is overwhelmed and so
there needs to be a healing process that
you go through within yourself in order
to re-establish connection amongst
different levels of developments from
the brainstem up towards the limbic
system and the frontal lobes the cortex
these systems need to be fully
integrated in order to have an internal
sense of connection which then relates
to your ability to connect with those
outside of yourself as you progress
through that journey and that requires
the overcoming of fear because these
early evolutionary centers of the human
the system the central nervous system
are very much predicated on the
certainty of the survival function which
has the fear of non survival and
Herenton the scripting there so you've
got to look at how that's developed over
your life and how the fear of it not not
working out or not making it as kind of
a conditioned reflex in us as we
interact with the world and so you know
some personality psychologists and Tim
wheeler Tim Leary in the 1960s actually
developed a a circuit model of the
nervous system and consciousness in
which the first four circuits he related
to normal psychology the normal levels
of development of human psychology and
they were very much systems based on
fear of not surviving fear of not
acquiring control of resources that kind
of a thing fear of not understanding
symbol associations understanding your
situation fear of are not reproducing so
there are all these inherent fears and
so the therapeutic process would ideally
involve going back and understanding
what it means to recognize how these
areas of development have been
conditioned throughout your life in a
way that could be error-prone and the
propensity for fear might be maximized
if that error-prone so by going back and
healing at each level you can look at
okay what does it mean to overcome the
stress response system through yoga or
martial arts or whatever so you have
control when it's stimulated and you
maintain a sense of control and so the
fear propensity is minimized and so you
can master you know what does it mean to
maintain the master of your emotions
emotion regulation and to understand
your situation in the universe the sense
of logical analysis and language use at
that level you know the greater
coherence you develop amongst these
systems and the greater sense of
integration the more you're able to
overcome the inherent fears they can
develop in our survival environment and
work towards going up them as little
hierarchy towards self-actualization or
individualization
in fashion as Jung called it towards
overcoming fear and embracing the love
that can await us as we you know
resonate with our environment the people
in it and their journeys and hopefully
achieve some kind of a resonant state in
which love can really be embraced and
actualized as a creative potentiality
beautiful okay so we have many different
aspects of ourselves that can be out of
balance with each other that may be a
better way to put it might be that some
aspects of our psychology some things we
come to think about the world that are
important for our security or even
before we think of basic sense of
mapping onto the world that's expected
that we associate with security the
feeling of home you know as a child just
the presence of your parents the the
smell of your house these associations
that we consider with safety which sort
of need to be there to form the bedrock
of what enables a young organism to go
out or to be curious about something
else in their experience to then learn
and then grow what seems to happen is
when a baseline level of security is
compromised becomes difficult to
integrate new experiences in something
continuous I want to come if you could
say a little bit about what your work
which is really more of a vocation I
think consists of
so to sum that up quite briefly and then
if you could say some of the things
you've picked up that are really the
bedrock conditions of what need to be
present in order to come into connection
with yourself enough so that you then
can begin to let's say move towards a
direction of being genuinely open to
situations in the world that might
challenge you that seems to be a really
fundamental thing that we all need to
become very capable at really develop
our sovereignty in being able to
experience things that challenge us but
to be able to hold that in consciousness
and learn rather than immediately
respond unless of course it's time to
immediately respond you know there's
times when it's appropriate is to
immediately lash back or run or whatever
it happens to be but in the in the realm
of ideas and in the realm of engaging
with other human beings in communication
the more we can be present with what is
the more we can maintain a continuity in
relationship the more we can maintain
and develop connection toward some of
these higher potentialities so I guess
what I'd like to do is can is to present
some of the bedrock conditions of
sovereign or competent functioning is
connection within ourselves it's
development within ourselves which then
enables a sort of effective relationship
with others and the world more broadly
here I'd like to just reaffirm that
humans have incredible potential
and this is something that isn't always
apparent to themselves and it's only
when you're able to sit down with them
and create a safe kind of space for them
to actually not feel like they need to
be on guard and defensive that you can
actually allow them to connect with
themselves and look at what it means to
become self-aware enough to realize
their potential and actualize that
through actions mm-hmm through error
correction through look at the patterns
of this is my thought action consequence
process and this is what isn't working
out okay what does that mean
you know if you were to keep doing that
what does that mean what can you change
in your thought process you know what
condition you to react in this way so
you know people come from a very noisy
world their data for today will is it's
that constantly bombarded by stimuli and
their systems are constantly on alert
you know this dress response system the
Olympics system everything is firing
firing firing and they into these social
spaces often they're trigger all their
childhood dynamics
I call it socio-ecological dynamic space
where that kind of Olympic system is
costly being fired up in social
situations and so they don't really get
the chance to move beyond that and
actually communicate on a more cerebral
level in a way that can lead to that
that sort of a progressive sense of
self-actualization and the interpersonal
context and so I deal in a therapeutic
situation it depends on a you know
someone's personality and their capacity
what their main challenges are and you
know what are the blockages at what
stages of development or what are their
main issues and their narrative or self
script and just enabling a sense of
connection with their self awareness you
know that's the first step really you
know are they what are they capable or
first you've got to work with their
capacity and accordingly with looking at
what risks there are and what's going to
maximize their health and well-being and
the contents of their capacity but if
they do have the capacity for self
awareness you know how can you provide
the space for that
that requires the art of interacting in
a way that takes them out of that
dynamic space and into a very valid
Eddings affirming space as they explore
themselves and you give them room and
space to do that right so cat works as a
dual diagnosis counselor that's the
first line on your biome but I wonder
how would you describe what it is you do
when you feel if you can presence what
it is to feel most meaningfully connect
like that the real meaningful output of
that from we meet people when it's like
what you do you know what you do for
work or what you do for this and then
all of a sudden it's this weird moment
of defining yourself often in
relationship to something that's not
that does not feel close to your heart
or your soul does not feel close to what
it really means for you to step forward
with integrity feeling full of who you
are in an authentic way and it's like oh
I work as a copywriter saying oh yeah
okay cool I mean that's not quite how I
experience my life day-to-day it's not
how I feel when I am most meaningfully
connected to myself and others so how
how how would you describe what your
role is if you were to speak to really
really the core meaning service that
you're providing for people or to the
greet which they've got the capacity for
it just provide the space for them to
make connections within themselves and a
meaningful and reframe things in a
meaningful way such that they can go out
into the world and change the way they
impulsively react to situations or at
least pause before they do react
impulsively and realize that hey this is
um an impulse we've looked at doesn't
work for me I need to just do some
breathing and bring myself into a more
of cerebral state taking myself out of
this dynamic or if I am in this dynamic
just say that I need to leave or keep it
simple
I know situations can escalate in that
dynamic space there's a lot of energy
there there's a
need for will to be exerted you know
because a lot of that dynamic space is
about you know disempowerment and
empowerment maybe tell us define what
you mean by dynamics a little bit so we
can get more of a handle on it I guess
it's an interpersonal kind of a mode of
State and relationship transactional
relationship with another right which is
often developed in the early childhood
in relation to the parent or caregiver
figures as your needs are supposedly
being met or not being met accordance
accordingly right so it's a stimulus and
response or sort of it's a stimulus
response conditioning that takes place
as we look to communicate ourselves to
the world as we look to relate to other
people as we relate to situations and
the key piece of wisdom really being how
do we cultivate that space between
stimulus and response so being able to
come into an awareness of what your
state is what your experience is once
something happens that all of a sudden
introduces or presents itself as a sort
of disconnection or a discontinuity to
something sort of flowing along I'm
having you know a conversation with
someone I care about and all of a sudden
something comes up and my subjective
state has changed
I don't feel on that same pulse it's not
flowing quite as easily that's something
that's come up and it's like oh I feel
different now like there's some kind of
map that has been a little bit
challenged by a piece of information and
often an immediate response to that
might be to reject it I mean might be
scary it might be pushing back on it and
then we condition those responses of
pushing back or repressing or with anger
sort of slapping down
something because it challenges what was
a state of connection a state of
security you know we can pass apart
security and connection but there's a
sense in which this something that seems
somewhat relevant to hold them together
there so it's how do we find how do we
develop the capacity to hold that space
to recognize that space between stimulus
and response so that then we can engage
in some kind of a new mode of
exploration or understanding of
ourselves in that context maybe we can
come to understand our relationship with
a particular drug a particular addictive
cycle from a slightly new perspective
and then maybe begin to try and embed
new behaviors there of course we can't
come across a new problem which is that
the environment and the habitats that
were a part of might not exactly be
allowing us so easily
to change ourselves because of course
these things is not like one little
moment of this connection and connection
here there's so much noise around us all
the time and even if we're not talking
about noise we're talking about just a
really deeply embedded environment and
history and culture that we're a part of
and we can talk about family dynamics
and aspects of the psyche that sort of
play out in these kind of repeatable and
story-like ways and then there are
steeped into the very stone around us
there are years of conditioned behaviors
in relationship to certain objects in
relationship to certain kinds of
gatherings in relationship to what it is
to gather like we are now you know we
can note the stage in front of us here
and there's something a bit
disconnecting about that to some degree
does seem to me to feel like that I mean
I I feel like I have to talk outside of
myself a little bit just to reach out so
to speak so that maybe so that maybe
there's something I can put out here
that then we can both grasp together and
so something I'm really quite interested
in as I know we've spoken about quite
of times is what does it take to involve
more and more people in sort of what
we're doing right now which is doing our
best to in a sense it feels a bit like a
modeling because you know there's an
audience here and we're up here on stage
and it's like we're modeling a sort of
exploration for the purpose of some sort
of value transmission but there's a
transmission element to it that's kind
of what we're used to in life you know
we turn on TVs we get messages from
radio we get taught things at school
it's often in a very top-down way it's
not often the case that we really come
into a sort of kind of participatory
knowing with others where through a
collaboration what the wisdom is to be
present at a really deep level that
might only be able to be present by
putting six people together in such a
way that the some of them becomes the
whole of them becomes more than the sum
of their parts so something I'm
interested in is how do we move from a
sort of a top-down message delivery to a
genuine kind of involvement that more
and more people can participate in and
that's something we're going to
experiment with quite shortly in the
second half of in the second half of
this evening but I know I sort of took
the conversation from one place to
another here sort of talking about the
stimulus response relationship and how
that might be a bedrock of what to
recognize in order to cultivate your own
capacity to enter into certain kinds of
creative relationships with people and
generally generally a transformative
relationship with the world that's a key
piece I wonder if there's anything else
from your work with people who are you
know particularly damaged with respect
to their own sense of connectivity to
themselves and the world what other
things have you found to be
really crucial ingredients to building
or enabling empowering human beings to
come more fully into themselves one
thing that really needs to be developed
so the degree to which an individual can
is an internal locus of control so when
you've got an it means as a child
there's the sense that something outside
of me didn't cater to my needs so this
is orientation towards the way other
people impact you and there's a tendency
to which problem thinking such as
blaming you know they didn't do this
they didn't do that and this is that's
why I am the way I am and this
perpetuates very toxic dynamics
generally speaking and very toxic
personality complexes prisons are filled
with people that have these complexes
and their minds are blaming everyone but
themselves for their reactive tendencies
and so if someone can develop through
the therapeutic process and internal
sense of iron control of my reactions
and through practice and the
neuroplasticity associated with practice
they can reaffirm corrections and their
thinking that lead to a mode of
responses that they will to have that
pause between stimulus and response and
moderate their reactions through
mindfulness whatever it might be through
taking their destructive energy of the
impulse and transmuting into a
constructive outlet whether it's some
movement sports whatever people have and
miners their mode of expression music
it's about recognizing that as a kind of
energy understanding that only they are
responsible for managing that energy if
they want to improve their lives and
avoid impacting other people as well and
then looking at their self-awareness of
actually taking that as a form of action
and actualizing how that plays out in
their lives right so they've got the
sternal sense of I am in control of my
reactions therefore I determine my
well-being and the path of my life as a
responsible person you know this is the
process of developing our responsibility
you are in control of your reactions
essentially regardless of whatever
damage happened as a childhood which
needs to be invalidated you know a lot
of people have Deniz just won't met his
children and that wasn't their fault
they were completely vulnerable that's
the price we pay for our potential with
our own large craniums you know we get
born in a completely vulnerable stage to
the price of potentiality is our
vulnerability to these conditioning
propensity but through therapeutic
growth we can learn to actually master
some of these destructive impulses and
turn them around into constructive
outlets to actually grow our sense of
responsibility self control and
potential facting in relation to the
world in a constructive and hopefully
progressive manner yeah that's beautiful
there's so many things and that's
something that came up powerfully there
is the notion that what enables us to
have such potential is the very thing
which makes us vulnerable to the
manipulation and narrowing and
ultimately torturing of it and that's
that's something to sit with there's
something deeply sad there's something
deeply sad about about potential
unfulfilled and I suppose there are two
components to that which are of course
interrelated and in some fundamental
sense I think we could have an
exploration where we spoke about these
two components as together but I think
now we can take them apart a little bit
and those two components are the the
individual element and what can I
develop what's the agency I can develop
in myself to become Who I am and then of
course also the habitats in the
environment which we're a part of and I
do feel that part of why we're gathered
here today it's certainly a motivating
factor for me and it does seem to be
something that is
becoming a heightened sense in the world
and it's becoming it's becoming a more
and more prescient lurking and looming
pulse shadow feeling and that is that
there's something about the habitat
there's something about the system that
we're a part of there's something about
the multi-layered system we're a part of
that is not conducive to enabling the
realization of our potential not only
individually but collectively the
reality is the world has been this way
for a very long time and I'm not saying
that there's sort of a top-down cabal of
elites that are necessarily responsible
for all of this although there are
certainly people in power who have a
vested interest in maintaining where
they are in that system of power but the
point fundamentally is that a system
itself can incentivize certain behavior
in it and so it's this individual
element and then what is incentivized by
the habitat as it's been constructed
over many stimulus and response
conditioned interactions over a very
long period of time and it's that
deep-seated sense of
where can I go what can I do how can I
really become who I feel I could be how
can I love more how can I have more time
with friends and family and big and and
express myself in in a way that feels
true but loving and not like I'm having
to shut my eyes to aspects of the world
which are cruel and perhaps ultimately
necessary to support my current standard
of living in this world and in this
society the fact is we are
interconnected and the more in fact one
comes into awareness of oneself them the
more I think one realizes the nature of
that connectivity and that seems to me
to be a huge huge thing and it seems
that a lot is changing and has to change
in really quite radical ways and I think
people know that you know obviously
people know that hundreds of thousands
of kids and people just on the streets
the other week in Melbourne to protest
climate extinction rebellion today as I
mentioned before but there's a sense in
which there's all this momentum for
change but we're not actually sure
really what to do and I wonder how and
the reason I'm saying this is to bring
it right back in again and to stress
that it's actually it seems like this
interpersonal capacity to communicate
itself regarding difficult ideas in a
context of what might scare you you know
that your children or your loved ones or
your parents are not safe perhaps or
that you might be complicit in someone
else's child or parent not being safe in
another part of the world these are
things which call into question really
are very like the very substructure of
the pillars of culture that support us
and that we come to call home and form
identity really
ships with and so it's just why it's so
so goddamn relevant to really engage in
you know in a deep sort of listening a
quietening of the noise in your own mind
and what emerges from then like I I
really don't know I don't want to be up
here speaking like this is some sort of
you know mountain that I've climbed a
very far up it's really not like that at
all this is really much more of an
invitation over a sustained period of
time to come together and genuinely sit
with what seems to be the case and even
that sounds a bit too definitive I'm not
saying we're going to crack what the
case is but what we can do is start to
put together interesting maps of things
and then feel what it's like to presence
that and then maybe begin to put some
pieces puts it put a few pieces together
and find some sort of way we can be in
relationship with each other that's
somehow more somehow more real because
there aren't such fundamental things
we're avoiding and I don't know what
that looks like I really really don't
it's a weight one big experiment but
what's interesting is that there are
many people around the world engaging in
something similar and so there's a
possibility of involving what we might
be able to create here with with the
online world in different communities
around the world
so anyway again I know I'm sort of
stepping away from a part of the flow in
a conversation but I would like just to
try and bring things back to how we are
in fact gathered here in an actual space
and we can engage with each other and
that's something I'm really looking
forward to doing in about 15 20 minutes
time so can I guess I guess moving
towards
you know might be two more questions
left perhaps if there's something but
this if you can maybe talk to that the
system or the habitat or elements of our
environment that you find most in
conducive to enabling connection if
there's anything that comes up there if
you feel this might be interesting to
put forward or really anything else at
all that well the reality is as you've
explained we've got many challenges
facing us with population densities
increasing the amount of noise that we
face on a daily basis the stimuli it can
be completely overwhelming for a lot of
people and it does have a threshold
point at which maybe it's not going to
function or sustain itself which is you
know what some people in various ways
seem to be aware of as they go to the
streets and protest that one thing that
comes to mind is what turns McKenna SID
and this is a bit of a late but I will
go back to the primal point here the
main thing is to remember is that we're
trapped in some kind of a work of art so
this is an ultimate point of
self-awareness and with that comes the
empowering sense of we can create an
image of our potentiality in whatever
way and the reason why I've got a
passion for metaphor and art is because
what can be represented is potential
through the lens of looking at the
levels and the levels at play as we sort
of understand ourselves and our
relationship with our environment you
know we've come out of this harmonic
connection in some sense in our history
into this sort of agriculture than
industrial civilization eventually and
in doing so we've as Rhonda said once
we've come out of the trees where there
wasn't enough and now we've actually got
enough with our technology you know
sense of knowledge of how to use that
but we've got all these adaptations to
this primitive hierarchical way of
relating to
objects and with industrial civility
realization came the sense of stuff is
what's meaningful and stuff gives us
reassurance and comfort and a sense of
meaning however shallow but in doing so
we've sacrificed so much when it comes
at a harmonic connection with nature
which seems to be essential for mental
health maintenance you know and with
this comes you know a lot of people
going back into nature and into shamanic
traditions and experiencing rituals this
thing has been lost in industrial
civilization in which they do experience
this enhanced connectivity with
themselves in their environment and
through that conduit meaning is realized
and communication and connection is
rediscovered in a way that industrial
civilization is kind of shut off and
disconnected us from you know with the
internet we've got a sense of connection
but are we connected to icons of
connection or actual actually connected
you know can we combine the icons of
connection through electronic mediums
with actually enhancing our
communicative capacity you know so we
need to assimilate a humaneness in our a
Wolfer connection at deeper levels with
whatever technologies we've got
intelligent use of technology can lead
us in great directions but until we
connect with ourselves in each other and
create better protocols for
communicating we're not gonna be able to
actualize our potentiality and the way
we really deeply desire it beautiful hmm
it's a really interesting contemplation
to consider just how deep the
relationship between connectivity and
this connectivity or connection and
disconnection really does lie how deep
is that in the substructure how deep is
that in the metaphysics of being itself
the
the constitutive relationships which
combine to create the gestalt and color
and beauty and wonder and terror and all
of this feeling that we are here
involved with involved in we are it
right it's not us somehow merely it
seems to me at least that we're not
merely contingent on a whole bunch of
stuff although of course we are meant
emergent from it in some fundamental
sense but we are it expressing itself we
are expressions of reality itself and
and so therefore there is something that
you know and I have not making this
argument I of course but really what I'm
trying to communicate with with us with
a sense of feeling is that there seems
to be and there seems there has to be
something in the nature of what it is to
experience itself and live itself and
listen and quieten which can enact or
enable a deep sense of participation
with reality itself which seems to be a
good bet as the key towards involving
ourselves again with a cycle of
participation in the world that looks to
be moving towards the direction of
harmony at least a little bit so to put
that in a way that's hopefully a bit
more simple there's a level of knowing
much deeper much more primary to the
level of knowing associated with beliefs
at this level up here but I am sitting
here that the world works in that
particular way right I'm a human being
with these sort of properties before we
form symbolic representation even
perhaps before we do representation
making at all
maybe not that's that's a deep
metaphysical question it's like this
connection and disconnection seems to
happen deep because it's involved in the
very the very realization of
transformation and development this is
something we actually have to accept our
own disconnection in order to come in
and to come into and awaken to different
parts of ourselves right there's a sense
in which there's a sense in which it's
not appropriate for me to present the
boy here who might be too afraid to
speak to you you know that boy has to
find a different way to contribute now
right and there's a sense in which to
leave behind the security of a childhood
is to well is to let go in some sense
that looks a little bit like a
disconnection maybe so it's not not so
not so not so simple I know I'm
introducing a couple a couple things
here in a bit of a a bit of a wander
around but that there's a way of knowing
deeper than beliefs participatory
knowing is think of like drama vague he
will refer to it as there's a mode of
being in the world way of listening and
being with and enacting that is
something we have within us that has
been borne along throughout billions of
years of evolution that we can present
and it's that it's that it's from that
source that I feel the that has to be
held that has to be in touch with we
have to be in touch with that should we
I think really wished to presence the
beginnings of solutions to some of the
problems we face so yeah I guess in
closing and come what do you make of
this idea of participatory knowing this
way of feeling into the very depths the
depths of who we are or allowing the
depths of what we are to emerge through
our well it's our potential emerging
through this deeper sense of
connectivity with
the flow of that around us it's it's
affected by everything around us and we
become conduits for what then is an
expression of a whole beyond just how we
would conceptualize ourselves at the ego
level maybe at the individual level
itself your self-awareness and you know
flow States through physical action in
the world engaging in a meaningful way
very essential and just a touch on some
of those things you mentioned one
important concepts that brings together
a lot of things I think is inspiration
we've got to find what inspires
ourselves and we've got to repeat it
like a diet you know because it's only
that which is inspiring that allows us
to move through that darkness you know
there's so much discomfort and distress
that we need this reference to
inspiration or an image of the ideal of
what we could be if we were to enjoy
that can get us to the place that we
want to be so I always like to emphasize
that we need to find what inspires us
whether it's quotes art the idea of our
ideal self the idea of love of
perfection of some kind whatever image
or affirmation inspires you needs to be
the conduit through which you relate to
the world as you face discomfort turmoil
distress whatever it might be and having
that as a reference allows you to endure
that a little bit more and that is
meaningful the endurance the ability to
sort of be present you know to get into
this flow of affirmation with reference
to this inspirational thing this image
or quote whatever it might be for you
and to practice there on a daily basis
you're making connections in your brain
and you're actually overcoming a lot of
the impulses that would otherwise weigh
you down you know that the metaphor of
the cocoon of darkness as we go through
the
mark of trying to survive the basic
conditions of this planet this ecosystem
this social container economic container
you know that is something to really
relate to but what kind of a
metamorphosis are we gonna have if we
don't find what it means to actually
build that self-awareness and focus our
minds in such a way that we can emerge
from that cocoon and you know then we
can explore what it means to spread our
wings and take flight and you know
individually that means something to
different everyone but collectively we
can inspire ourselves once we explore
and inside ourselves what it means to do
that first hmm beautiful so something to
be with something to inspire yourself
with something to hold a certain sort of
faith with through a process of
transformation transformation is
essential to our journey in life you
know we've got to learn what it means to
actually engage in transformation you
know yes of whatever support we need to
do that and self-awareness is one of the
beginning beginning points of that
developing our talents our relationship
with our qualities our potential you
know there's so much to began just
through self-awareness there's a
springboard through which we can engage
and more efficient or framing ways with
the world you know and there's all kinds
of things we can manifest if we set our
minds to it yeah beautiful well that
seems like a good place to end for this
part of this evening so it can't thank
you thank you so much